Now that the longest minute of the day,
every time we are here, is over. Welcome
to the finance committee meeting for May
4th. We're going to kick it off with
temporary resolution 4726.
I should just call this the Mr. Als
meeting water.
>> We should call it the Denise Cruz
meeting.
>> Well, that's fair.
>> He's here.
>> You just just stay up there. You don't
have to sit down each time.
>> Sorry I made you turn out tonight.
Uh, this resolution authorizes the
service safety director to enter into a
design bill contract for the energy
upgrade at Southwater Plant. Um, last
meeting you approved
um us to wave the RFQ process and enter
directly into negotiations. So, we have
received a draft contract. The law
director is reviewing it. We just wanted
to give you three readings as we um move
this project forward.
Any questions? It's pretty
straightforward.
>> Okay. 48.
Sorry, I didn't mean to take over the
meeting.
>> Oh, you're good.
>> Just making my notes. Temporary res
resolution 48 just-26
authorizes the service safety director
to advertise for bids for the Tiki Lane
waterline replacement project. Um this
is replacing the water line on Tiki from
Sheridan to Manmouth. As you recall,
we've had quite a few breaks in that
area and some leaks and the geyser last
summer. Um, so, um, we've been trying to
shoehorn this project in among all the
other ones. So, that we'll advertise for
bids in, uh, June and start construction
in September and it should be about six
weeks.
>> Denise, I have a question. What made
this become the priority? Was it the
fact that it would all those breaks or
was it on the list for a while and it
shot to the top of the list because of
all the breaks? it it's been on the
list, but yeah, when the geyser went up
last summer, that pushed it to the top
of the list of water lines we needed to
replace for preventative maintenance.
>> So, my follow-up question, are there a
lot of other ones on the list that have
a similar fate?
>> I can't tell you that for sure. Division
of Water does track their brakes. Um, so
they will come to me and say, "Hey, we
want to replace this water line." Um, in
the past, they have done it themselves
internally.
just when when they feel that there's a
need for it. Um, and because we're we're
so busy with other things, we've decided
to put this one up for bid and see how
it works.
>> Okay. Thank you.
>> I have a question, Mr. Chair.
>> Yes.
>> Um, Denise, uh, could you tell us please
what the uh, the current status of that
water line is? And let's say
hypothetically um, this project doesn't
get done uh, in the timetable you
described. What what do when do you
anticipate another failure occurring?
>> So the the water line currently has been
repaired
um and so we don't anticipate a fail. Um
a lot of times it's um freeze thaw and
thankfully we're past that. Um, in that
case in in the one last fall it it was a
line shift and a joint broke and water
gushed out. Um, so at this point we
don't anticipate another break, but we
know that there have been a number of
breaks on that line.
>> Thank you.
>> That line did break twice.
Three times. Yeah. And disrupted I
couldn't get Christiey's pizza for at
least 24 hours. So,
>> well,
>> anyway,
>> there's a daycare center that's on that
line and there's um a beauty shop and
>> Yeah.
>> And so, yes, it's
>> we need to fix it.
>> Yes.
>> Any other questions? I'm sorry, Cordy.
>> All right. Any other questions?
Any other comments? Miss Woody,
>> I'll just add one additional comment
that uh Councilman Als, you are correct
that it did break multiple times and it
broke in different locations each time,
which is what makes us want to get this
fixed quickly because we anticipate that
it could continue to break in different
points because of the age and the
condition.
>> And they also break because of extreme
heat. So, it's not just the freeze and
thaw, it's the extreme heat as well.
>> That that one happened I think in the
summer. The first one, the geyser was
Yeah. All right. Now I'm done.
>> Okay. I have both of first two is three
readings,
right?
>> Yes.
>> Okay.
>> 4926.
>> 49-26
relates to the Tiki uh waterline issue.
This authorizes the service safety
director to execute a engineering
contract amendment for construction
administration resident inspection and
asbuilt plans for that water line.
>> Okay. Same project, second piece of
legislation
>> and three readings also.
>> Three readings.
>> Okay.
Any questions on that one?
Seeing none, 5026,
I have a question.
>> Yes, ma'am.
>> Denise, um, you gave me a really great
answer via email, so I'm actually going
to ask you again so you can say it for
everyone because I had a question about
the fact that it had stated that 3.8
million was at the 50% design and I
wanted you to give clarity on the what
that means for the totality of the
project.
>> Okay. Uh, that's on uh resolution 50-26.
That's the Lawrence Street pump station
project. Um we have a pump station
that's located across from the sanit
sanitation maintenance facility and um
it's reached the end of its life but
more importantly there's a big piece of
property for economic development that
we cannot serve easily. They can get
service but they have to pump all the
way up to the railroad tracks. So this
pump station will allow development in
that industrial
um area. Also we are at 50% design and
the estimated cost was 3.8 million. Um
that 3.8 million includes a lot of
contingencies
as we finish things up like the the
controls and the electronics. Pumps are
always a problem. We never know what the
pricing of pump's going to be until the
um biders start getting bids in. Um and
we're still working out things like um
one of the issues we had at 50% design
was access and we've decided to access
it through the transfer station. So now
we're trying to figure out where we want
to move the fence. So there's all those
little costs that we've we've got a
bundle of money in there. We just don't
know exactly what they are. So, at um at
90% design, we'll have all of those laid
out and we'll be able to put a more
accurate price on it.
Any questions on this one?
I do have a couple questions. The what I
and I might have overlooked it. What how
are we paying for this project?
>> This is being paid by cash through the
wastewater reserve fund. And then since
you brought it up with the so you're
hoping that the so the plan is the new
pump station will help service economic
development in the industrial park
>> in the um South Ewain Street area.
>> Yes. That so like across the street
potential across the street is any of
that
I guess I'm going to I'm going to bring
in the port here because I'm staring at
Stephanie Bosco. Is that project
something that the port would be
involved with in terms of
you know I guess mitigating some of that
price?
>> Th this has not been discussed. So so
part of the price would be the capacity
fee that would be charged when somebody
makes a connection. So, if we have a
large user make a connection on that
empty piece of property, they'll pay a
fairly hefty capacity charge for the
privilege of doing that.
>> Okay.
Thank you.
Any other questions?
All right. That is all we have for new
resolutions. Thank you, Denise.
>> Thank you.
>> Thank you, Mr. Als.
>> Uh, we have one new ordinance. It's
coming. as temporary ordinance 1126
coming through law committee, Miss
Smiley.
>> Thank you, Mr. Chair. So, this is an
annual piece of legislation, my
understanding, and it's a request that
was sent to us from the codification
company that is going to make um the
Lancaster codified ordinance language
near the Ohio Revised Code with all the
new laws that were passed between
December 9th and December 31st, December
9th of 2024 to December 31st of 2025.
Um, so this company is just basically
going to be reorganizing and reumbering
so that way the Lancaster codified
ordinance matches.
Anything to add, this law director,
I'll just say you all already approved
the changes in terms of the text that
changed and this is just basically to
make it now numerical and sequential. So
they just need to fix that aspect of it.
That's all it is. Thanks.
Any questions?
Seeing none, that is all for ordinances.
Moving on to department updates. Do we
have anyone here who would like to give
a department update?
Mr. Shaw,
good evening. It's construction season,
so I thought I would update on three of
our construction projects.
Our 2026 paving is underway. The Shelly
Company was awarded that contract. I
think most of the streets that are going
to be paved have at least milled or
placed the first course of asphalt, the
intermediate course, and they'll be
doing the final course in the coming
weeks. We're hoping they'll be wrapping
it up by the end of May, maybe by
Memorial Day, we'll be mostly finished
with that project.
So that's exciting. Um Arbor Valley
Drive, another one that Strawer
um construction they got that project
that starts well they're allowed to
start on May 28th when school is out. Uh
that'll be a summerl long project, a
closure of Arbor Valley Drive with
um essentially a new road, new curbs,
new bike path, um new sidewalks, new
drainage. So that's a large project that
we're excited to do and hopefully have
it all wrapped up when the school opens
up this fall so that um we have a new
school and a new road to get there.
We've been working on that for a while.
We've got five different pots of money
to pay for that. We've got a a high
public works grant. We've got some 3M
money in it for the asphalt. We've got
storm water money in it. Um sidewalk
money in it. We we reached in a lot of
different pockets to make that happen.
Um
the 6th Avenue Bridge, this one was
awarded to complete general
Um bids were higher than we had hoped.
We got one bidder. U luckily we got more
money from the state. We asked and they
gave us more money to cover that
overage. This one they intend to start
June 1st and it'll be a full closure of
6th Avenue. We've allowed for a 19-w
week closure.
Um, so that is good to see that
happening, although it will not be fun
with Sixth Avenue closed down all
summer. So, we'll have more traffic on
um Fair Avenue and I believe Steven has
a storm water project on Frederick
Street also. I don't know if that's a
full closure or not, but that's in that
that same neck of the woods.
Also, I wanted to talk about um East
Chestnut Street or East and West
Chestnut Street. So, the safety
committee has kind of been talking about
Chestnut Street and a solution to two
problems that we have. One is
between
uh Columbus Street and Broad Street.
It's too narrow. You have people parking
on the curbs and mirrors getting hit and
the fire department actually don't
doesn't go that way because they don't
want to clip mirrors or worse strike
pedestrians because when you have that
narrow of a street, two-way traffic, it
gets a little sketchy when folks pop out
behind the cars.
Another problem we have on Chestnut
Street is the intersection of High
Street and Chestnut.
That really should be a four-way stop.
It is not because when you're coming up
the hill, people get stuck or they can't
get moving in the wintertime,
especially.
So, to solve that problem, it is the way
it is now. It's a two-way stop with High
Street stopping and Chestnut continuing,
but because of the poor visibility and
the grades, people don't treat it that
way. They think they're supposed to
stop. So, it's a really awkward
intersection with a lot of
close calls, probably some fender
benders that don't get reported. Um, so
not not dangerous, but not good. So, by
making Chestnut Street a one-way street
westbound
from High Street to Columbus,
that becomes a three-way stop, which
will be great for that intersection. And
obviously with only one lane of traffic,
the narrow street and the other block um
takes away that problem as well. Um the
side benefit of it is there will be more
parking because as you come down the
hill, you'll be able to park on both
sides of the street. So,
in front of the post office, it'll add I
think it's 20 spaces to the to those two
blocks of Chestnut.
The folks at the post office are excited
about it because they try to get, you
know, they try to restrict the way
people turn out of there and it it
really it's just a suggestion. People
don't really follow it and it gets kind
of uh it gets to be a mess there and
that it'll improve that situation as
well.
We think most of the traffic will use
Walnut Street. If you're trying to go
eastbound on Chestnut, Walnut Street has
plenty of capacity. Not a lot of traffic
on Walnut Street. We don't think that'll
be a real problem. So,
I think LDOT, well, I know L Dot is
going to be doing the work. We're going
to have Griffin paving in to do the the
striping, but Lot will be doing the
signing. I think Charlie, what day is
that? June 3rd.
>> June 3 is the the day that we're going
to do that. I think letters have already
went out and we're going to do door
hangers on all the businesses. I think
we probably talked to a good good
portion of those.
Um, so any questions on any of that?
Sorry, when you said Chestnut, is it
from High Street all the way to Columbus
>> 33 or is it to Columbus? Columbus
>> to Columbus. So, the first block from
Memorial to Columbus will remain a
two-way street and then between from
High Street East in front of St. Mary's
and the fire station that will also
remain
>> two-way. Two-way.
>> Kurt, I have a question about Walnut and
High. Will there will that become a
four-way stop? No, that'll be a two-way
stop the same as it is now.
>> Okay. So, turning left, there's usually
residential cars that go right up to the
curb. Will there be signage so that way
they don't anymore so we can see
visibility turning left?
>> We'll take a look at that. I'm not sure
I understand the situation. So, you're
saying when they turn left on the Yeah.
>> on the high street,
>> it's hard when people are coming down
high because of the cars that are so
close to the curb there.
>> Oh, I see.
>> To the intersection.
>> Okay. Just something to consider.
>> All right. Thank you. We'll look that
>> I like that you do have to creep out
there a little bit.
>> Nobody likes creeping section, too.
>> Mr. OG,
>> uh if you're going from
uh High to Columbus,
uh why not go from Maple and make it one
way past St. Mary's?
>> We don't have an issue there. and it's
not too narrow. We don't we don't know
of any issues to make it one way. We
prefer to have two-way streets because
it for the folks that live on those
streets, they'd like to be able to have
options when they're entering and
exiting.
So, because there wasn't an issue, we
didn't consider that.
just thinking through the school zone it
might have made a difference, but
>> I I think the the eastbound traffic
because the those two blocks are going
to be one way. I don't you'll still be
able to go eastbound, but there won't be
as many people because if you were going
to go east, you would probably go
Walnut. There's no reason to turn and go
up to Chestnut. You're probably just
going to continue on Walnut until you
get to Maple.
So, I think it'll improve things for the
school and the fire station as well. Um,
without actually making it a one-way
street.
>> That's that's actually just one comment
I wanted to make was that I don't know
that you'd want to make it a one-way
street in front of the fire station. You
would need the fire trucks to be able to
go both ways.
>> True.
>> Any other questions for Mr. Shank?
Seeing none, thank you very much. Thank
you.
>> Any other department updates?
Mr. Deetsz.
Good evening, council. Uh, I just want
to mention something that you guys may
have seen in the news lately, and that's
fuel prices. Anybody notice their fuels
costing a little bit more? Um, the
city's not immune. So, just to give you
guys a heads up as you're having your
committee meetings, um the departments
that have vehicles have a line item
that uh they put money into to pay for
gas and other fuels and oils. Just have
them keep an eye on those. Um, just to
give an example, on
February 27th, the day before the
excursion started overseas,
um, our cost um, for fuel for unleted
was 245 a gallon. Last Saturday through
ODOT through their bidding process, it's
415 per gallon. That's about a 69%
increase. and diesel, same time period,
went from 339 to 605. That's about an 87
or 78% increase. So, um, as we're
nearing mid-season, um, for everybody's
budgets, um, they're going to have to
keep an eye on on things because if not,
they'll be coming to you in the fall
saying, "Hey, I need more money,"
whether it's going to be moving some
around or new appropriations. So, just
uh, keep that in your back pocket. Any
questions?
We'll see any. Thank you.
>> All right.
>> For souring the mood,
>> any other department updates?
>> Go ahead,
>> ma'am.
>> Thank you,
>> um, just wanted to let everybody know
that, um, the young man who applied for
our position as an assistant prosecutor
passed the bar on May 24th or sorry,
April 24th. uh and we offered him a job
last week and he accepted. So, we are
looking forward to him starting. Uh he
won't actually be sworn in until May
18th. So, he can't start with us until
May 19th, but on May 19th, he will start
uh his training. Hopefully do that for
about a month before I bring him to you
and have you go ahead and formally um
give him the approval and sign off. But
I just wanted to let everybody know that
that we're very excited to welcome
somebody new. He went to the University
of Akran with um one of our parillegals
actually and that's how he heard about
the job and then went to the University
of Toledo College of Law. Um but brand
new graduate looking forward to the the
spirit and the initiative that a a young
person will bring into the office. So
just want to let everybody know. Thanks,
>> Mrs. Woody.
So, to continue the good the good news,
since Tim got all the the bad news out,
I just wanted to quickly say thank you
to DDL and to all of the council members
and to all of the city employees who uh
volunteered with the hundreds of other
volunteers in our downtown area to make
our downtown the city of downtown city
look absolutely beautiful and clean. And
we really appreciate all the effort that
everyone put in. and Amanda, thank you
and DDL for your charge on that because
we truly appreciate that. And then the
other thing I wanted to say is it is
National Public Service Recognition
Week. And so I would encourage uh the
members of the public, if you see any of
the city employees and your council
members out and about this week, please
make sure you tell them thank you for
all of their public service that they uh
put in tirelessly day in and day out.
>> Thank you very much.
Any other
department updates?
Seeing none, we'll move to council
meeting prep. As you can see,
I'm sitting here again. That's two weeks
in a row. Two meetings in a row.
Yeah, I'm staring at you. That's really
not your fault, though. So, we'll give
you a pass on that one. Um, it should
breeze right through. Um, we have no
legislation to actually pass. So, it's a
bunch of boring readings and we should
be moving through that pretty quickly.
Do we have any other discussion items
for finance?
Seeing none, I will look for a motion to
adjurnn.
>> So moved.
>> Second.
>> And we are adjourned at 6:24. We'll
start the regular meeting on time at
6:30.
The Frankie Smith Funeral Home and
Crematory in Lancaster. and the Johnson
Smith Funeral Home in Baltimore have a
long and wonderful history of serving
our community. Feel free to give us a
call at 740653652.
Stop in and see us at either of our two
locations, 405 North Columbus Street in
Lancaster and 207 South Main Street in
Baltimore. Respect for tradition, regard
for change.
Life moves fast and Buckeye is here to
keep you moving. New dream job?
Celebrate with a ride that feels just as
exciting. Passing the keys to your new
teen driver? Treat yourself to an
upgrade you'll love. Family getting
bigger? Buckeye's got the perfect
spacious, safety packed vehicle for
every new arrival. Wherever life takes
you, Buckeye Nissan, Georgeesville
Nissan, Buckeye Honda, and Buckeye
Toyota are ready to drive you forward.
Your life, your car, your choice. Choose
Buckeye.
my uh gentle reflection. Couple things.
Continue your Art of Neighboring work. I
appreciate it because I I'm certain some
of you are doing it. So, Art of
Neighboring, continue with that. Also,
happy Star Wars Day. It is May the 4th.
So, for you Star Wars geeks, happy Star
Wars Day. And then tomorrow is voting
day. So please make sure you get out and
do your civic duty. And that's kind of
the art of neighboring as well. So there
you go. All right. Let's do the pledge
of allegiance, please.
I pledge algiance to the flag of the
United States of America and to the
republic for which it stands. One nation
under God, indivisible, with liberty and
justice for all.
>> Call the meeting to order and we will
start with roll call, please.
>> Mr. Als here.
>> Mr. Bishack here.
>> Mr. Carr here.
>> Miss Cohen here.
>> Mrs. Coupe
>> here.
>> Mr. Nisley
>> Mr. OG
>> here.
>> Mr. Skoonover
>> Miss Smiley
>> here.
>> And Mr. Sully
>> The record reflect that all 10 members
are present.
Reading and disposal of the journal.
>> I have regular meeting minutes dated
April 20th, 2026.
>> Uh thank you, Mr. President. I move that
we receive and file the journal.
>> Second. We have a motion and second to
accept the read or yeah reading and
disposing of the journal. All in favor
please signify by saying I.
>> I.
>> All post same sign. Motion carries.
Reports of city officials.
>> I have four of them. I have series of
emails between Ch. Snyder, Law Director
Hall, Council Clerk Scott and Paul
Kuinsky of the Division of Liquor
Control, dated April 21st, 2026
regarding liquor license, liquor control
licensing. Um, email dated April 23rd,
2026 regarding TWWLA
report on city hall submitted by service
safety director Woody. Email dated April
24th, 2026 regarding City of Lancaster's
community development programming survey
submitted by grants manager Michelle
McCrady. Email dated May 1st, 2026
regarding background information on
temporary resolutions 47-26,
48-26, 49-26, and 50-26
submitted by environmental engineer
Denise Cruz.
>> Mr. Thank you, Mr. President. And I move
that we receive and file the uh reports
of city officials.
>> Second.
>> We have a motion and a second to accept
and file the reports of city officials.
All in favor, please signify by saying
I.
>> I.
>> All oppose, same sign. Motion carries.
Do we have any communications?
>> I do have one. I have a voicemail um
dated April 27th, 2026. Um M regarding
the liquor license u from QuickMart. The
gentleman had called and left a message
and I ended up foring it on to law
director's office.
>> Okay,
Mr. Bisjack.
>> Thank you, Mr. President. I move that we
receive and file the communications.
>> Second.
>> We have a motion and a second to accept
and file the communications. All in
favor, please signify by saying I.
>> I.
>> All oppose, same sign. Motion carries.
>> Do we have any special presentations?
>> There are none this evening.
Are there any petitions and memorials?
>> There are no petitions or memorials this
evening.
>> All right. Now is the time we set aside
for voters or taxpayers to address
counsel. Are there any members in the
audience that would like to address us?
And that would be yes and you know the
rules. Ma'am,
>> you make assumptions. No, I know the
rules. Thank you. Good evening, council.
Um, first off, I want to uh uh ask for a
mindset shift. When uh Mr. Shank was up
here talking about Chestnut Street, he
kept referring to how narrow that street
was. That street is the same width than
it's been um since probably before many
of us were born. It is not a narrow
street. What's happening and why we're
experiencing more problems now than we
have historically is that vehicles are
larger than they ever have been before.
So, when you have a lifted Dodge Ram
pickup truck, um uh that I mean, I know
I'm not tall, but I'm 5'4 and when it's
coming up to here, um they're parking up
on the curb and their mirrors might get
hit because it's a giant vehicle and our
streets being a historic city were not
designed for these giant vehicles. So, I
don't think it's a narrow street, but I
do think it provides challenges, which
is why I'm ever so grateful from a
safety perspective because I do believe
that it was a as someone I downtown
cleanup day, we came home and I'm not
sure those of you that were helping out
on downtown cleanup day, there was a
giant uh uh and and dangerous wreck um
where they had to tow both vehicles away
on that Saturday. Um, and I believe
that's the sixth one um um in 2026 if I
if I have my numbers correct. So, I am
very grateful for to council um and the
city of Lancaster for taking that safety
concern seriously. Uh it will make a
huge difference in my opinion and I
really appreciate it. Uh I also wanted
to carry uh uh safety service director
Woody kind of stole my thunder. Uh we
had over 300 volunteers for downtown
cleanup day and we had a wonderful
showing from city council on three
separate teams and it was wonderful to
see so many folks from area businesses,
community leaders like yourselves
rolling up your sleeves together. Some
of you misplaced your glasses for only a
spell, but then you found them and they
weren't in the mulch. They were in your
inside pocket. I'm not mentioning any
names, but I'm so grateful for all of
your work because it truly does make a
difference. And we had such positive
feedback from community members who saw
their representatives out there. Thank
you. Um uh they I worked them hard. Uh
and so I really really appreciate all of
you for doing that and it looks
beautiful and fantastic. So thank you.
Thank you. Thank you. I appreciate it.
>> Thank you very much. Anyone
else?
Keep it in the family. Mr. Everett,
>> this makes it easy because I can just
use those little hash marks on my
signin. Um, I wanted to echo uh Miss
Amanda Everett's uh thanks to city
council and the city for taking some
action on Chestnut Street. I bought the
house there in 2007 and I have lost two
cars to uh crashes there. Uh both
totaled by parking in front of my house.
Uh, I have sat outside with a kid
wrapped in a blanket on Christmas Eve,
uh, giving him cookies that we had from
inside while his mom was taken away in
the squad uh, due to a crash there. Um,
and on a less severe basis, just pretty
much every time I come home, I pick up
pieces of plastic that are in the street
uh, in the yard or in the park. So, um,
slowing things down there will go a
great deal, uh, towards lessening the
impact. Uh, Kate doesn't like creeping,
but, um, I think that seeing people
creep out, um, is the way to go. Um, I'm
amazed and horrified when I'm sitting on
my front porch and I see somebody go 45
miles an hour down or up high street and
not even pause that light. uh they roll
the dice and more often than not they uh
do not land well for them. So, thank
you.
>> Y to echo that sentiment. I've picked my
grandkids up from their parents being
t-boned in that intersection and uh that
is a traumatic experience for sure. So,
anyone else to address council this
evening?
Okay, thank you very much for coming and
we're going to move on. Are there any
reports of standing committees?
>> I have three this evening. I have code
enforcement and zoning committee meeting
date added um dated April 29th, 2026
submitted by Mr. Sully. Law committee
meeting minutes dated April 22nd, 2026
submitted by Miss Smiley. And finance
committee meeting agenda dated May 4th,
2026, submitted by Mr. Skunberg.
>> Mr. Bisjack.
>> Thank you, Mr. President. I move that we
receive and file the reports of standing
committees. Second
>> a motion and a second to accept and file
the reports of standing committees. All
in favor, please signify by saying I.
>> I.
>> All oppose, same sign. Motion carries.
>> There are any reports of special
committees.
>> There are no reports.
>> We don't have any public hearings this
evening. So, we're going to move on to
reading of resolutions. We have no third
readings. So, we're going to start with
the second reading of temporary
resolution 4126,
>> a resolution to authorize the mayor to
enter into a contract with the Fairfield
County General Health District for
public health services. This through
finance committee, Mr. Skinnerford and
Mr. Als
>> and that'll be the second of three
readings on temporary resolution 4126.
4226,
>> a resolution to appropriate from the
unencumbered balance and amend the
certificate of appropriations with the
county auditor in the general fund
for the retirement within the Lancaster
Fire Department and to declare an
emergency. This is through safety
committee, Mr. Bisjack and Mr. Al.
>> Mr. Bisjack.
>> Thank you, Mr. President. This is the
second of three readings.
>> Second of three readings on temporary
resolution 4226.
4326.
A resolution to appropriate from an
unencumbered balance and amend the
certificate of appropriations with the
county auditor in the 0.15 fire levy
fund 2046 and to declare an emergency.
Again, this is through safety committee,
Mr. Bisjack and Mr. Sully.
>> Mr. President,
>> yeah, I'm sorry I skipped right over the
this one. I'm looking at another one.
I'm like, what? It's 4326. So, Mr.
Bisjack.
>> No, thank you, Mr. President, this will
be the second of three readings.
>> Sorry, it wasn't you, it was me. 4326.
That's second. Okay. Temporary
resolution 4426.
>> A resolution authorizing this service
safety director to advertise for bids
for the Southwater Plant backflow of
valves project into declared emergency
through water pollution control
committee. Mr. Als and Miss Cohen.
>> Mr. Als readings. Second of three
readings on temporary resolution 4426.
Temporary resolution 4526.
>> A resolution to increase receipts
appropriate funds from the storm water
utility reserve 6019. Amend the
certificate of other sources and
appropriations with the county auditor
and authorized payments of bills and
then
with then certificates for the Ohio
water development authority loan for the
Frederick State Street sewer separation
project. This again through water water
pollution control committee. Mr. Als and
Miss Cohen.
>> Mr. Als
>> second of three readings.
>> Second of three readings on temporary
resolution 4526.
Temporary resolution 4426.
>> 4626,
>> sorry. A resolution authorizing the
service safety director to enter into a
contract for engineering services on the
Columbus Street and Wilson Avenue sewer
separation project is through water
water pollution control committee. Mr.
Als and Mr. Bisjack.
>> Mr. Als,
>> second of three readings.
>> Second of three readings on temporary
resolution 4626.
Moving on to first readings of
resolutions with temporary resolution
4726.
>> A resolution to authorize the service
safety director to enter into a design
build contract for energy upgrade grant
funds for the southwater treatment plant
rehabilitation. This through water water
pollution control committee Mr. Als and
Miss Cohen.
>> Mr. Als first of three readings.
>> First of three readings on temporary
resolution 4726.
Moving on to temporary resolution 4826.
>> A resolution authorizing the service
safety director to advertise for bids
for the Tiki Lane water line replacement
project is through water water pollution
control committee. Mr. Als and Miss
Cohen.
>> Mr. Als,
>> first of three readings. It's
>> first of three readings on temporary
resolution 4826.
Temporary resolution 4926. A resolution
authorizing the service safety director
to execute an engineering contract
amendment for the construction
administration services for the Tiki
Lane water line replacement project. Mr.
Water and Water Pollution Control
Committee, Mr. Als and Mr. Bisjack.
>> Mr. Als,
>> first of three readings.
>> First of three readings on temporary
resolution 4926.
Temporary resolution 5026. A resolution
authorizing the service safety director
to advertise for bids for the Lauren
Street pump station replacement project.
This is your water water pollution
control committee, Mr. Als and Mr.
Bisjack.
>> Mr. Als,
>> first of three readings.
>> First of three readings on temporary
resolution 5026.
I don't believe we have any other
resolutions to come before council. So,
we'll move on to reading of ordinances.
We have no third reading of ordinances.
will start with the second reading of
temporary ordinance 926,
>> an ordinance to authorize the mayor to
acquire permanent and temporary ride
ofway as necessary for the East Main
Street Shoulder widening and new
sidewalks projects known as the East
Main Street FAI- US22-15.58
project. This is through public works
committee. Mr. Carr and Miss Smiley.
>> Mr. Carr.
>> This is second of three readings. Second
of three readings on temporary ordinance
926.
Temporary ordinance 1026.
>> An ordinance providing the issuance and
sale of notes in the maximum principal
amount of $6,400.
I'm sorry, $6,400,000
in anticipation of the issuance of bonds
for the purpose of paying the cost of
the renovation and rehabilitation of the
city hall building and otherwise
improving the site. Therefore, together
therefore together together with all
necessary pertinances thereto in
declaring an emergency is through
finance committee Mr. Skoover and Mr.
Sully.
>> And that'll be the second reading of
temporary ordinance 1026.
Moving on to first readings with
temporary ordinance 11:26,
>> an ordinance approving the editing and
inclusion of certain ordinances as parts
of the various components codes of the
cod codified ordinances in the Lancaster
of Lancaster, Ohio and to declare an
emergency through law committee, Miss
Smiley and Mr. Carr.
>> Miss Smiley.
>> Thank you, Mr. President. First of three
readings.
>> So first of three readings on temporary
ordinance 11:26.
We do not have any additional ordinances
to come before council this evening. I
see no table legislation. Does anyone
have any unfinished business to discuss?
No. All right. Thank you. Any new
business anyone would like to discuss?
Seeing none, we'll take this opportunity
to go around the table as per usual. Any
updates from council members on their
committees, starting with Mr. Sully,
>> code enforcement and zoning, we're
having a meeting on May 15th at 7:30 in
the uh
>> special meeting on
>> it's sort of Yeah, it's out of schedule.
We'll call it that.
>> Okay,
>> Mr. Bisjack.
>> Thank you, Mr. President. safety
committee meeting will be meeting in
June, uh, first Friday in June, in fact.
So, look forward to seeing everybody
there. I have no new business to share
with the body at this time. Thank you.
>> Thank you,
>> Miss Cohen.
>> Uh, nothing new. Administrative
committee meeting is May 22nd at 2 p.m.
in the 1897 conference room.
>> Thank you, Mr. Als. Anything new besides
all your legislation we just went
through? You have seven pieces of
legislation moving through council right
now. I don't think we need an update. I
think we just had one.
>> Agreed.
>> Miss Smiley.
>> Um, no update from the law committee,
but I did want to take a moment to say
thank you to the safety service director
and to Stephanie Bosco with the Port
Authority who were guest speakers at Amy
and I, our town hall that we had last
week for the third and the fifth ward.
It was wonderfully attended and we
appreciated your insights and the
knowledge that you shared. So, thank
you.
>> You got that from the heart of
neighboring, didn't you?
>> Sure did.
>> Yes.
>> I'm going to take credit anyways because
that's awesome. Well done. All right.
Um,
you see it. We went through all of it. I
don't have any additional updates for
finance. Mr. dog.
>> Still no updates from my non-existent
committees.
>> Anything you want to share at all?
>> Art of neighboring anything?
>> I saw you at I saw you at T-ball or
baseball.
>> My son got his first home run.
>> Yeah. So, there you go.
>> Meet you.
>> Um
>> I didn't realize how many kids played
over at Cherry Street Park. Oh, yeah.
Yeah,
>> it was a little chilly but
>> busy there. And a big shout out to the
uh Lancaster Youth Baseball Association.
They have taken Mary Burnham Park and
>> thank you
>> uh really uh
have uh
rehabbed that and made it into a
wonderful baseball park. Uh so if you
get the chance to go there and watch a
little league game, uh worth its time
and uh as matter of personal interest,
be nice to your local umpires.
>> Fair enough. I've never been so excited
to see a 5-year-old hit the ball and run
to first base while everybody is looking
up in the air um while the ball rolls by
them. But that's a whole another story.
Mr. Carr,
>> I think u Mr. Shank did a thorough job
of covering all the projects that are
happening and thank Mr. Deetsz for
throwing the downer on the fuel prices
and uh
>> that's all we got.
>> Perfect. Thank you very much, Mr.
Nisley.
>> Yeah, thank you, Mr. President. Yeah,
service committee will meet on May 14th
in the 1897 conference room in city
hall. I anticipate we'll have plenty of
department updates to go through.
updates on Bowowers Park, for example,
um some other happenings around some of
the departments there. And uh that's it.
Thank you.
>> Thank you, Mrs. Hoop.
>> Thank you, Mr. President. Um economic
development just met last Thursday. Um
we discussed some legislation that's
going to be coming um including the West
End TIF. There's going to be an
amendment. Um, also the port authority
is building a spec building and so we
will be voting on a development
agreement. Um, there were a few annual
pieces from community development
regarding the annual action plan for the
block grant and the chip grant. And then
we also get to hear from um, visit
Fairfield County. um and they're
promoting a lot of um 250 anniversary um
events this summer. So check out their
website for that. Um we hear from the
chamber who is um in the middle of their
ribbon cutting season as he called it.
Um they're also celebrating their 40th
year um being the chamber. So I thought
that was neat. Um and last we have DDL.
Um, there was a ton of stuff with DDL,
but just to summarize, they're starting
a youth passport program for downtown.
Um, their free Saturday cinema, which is
the second Saturday every month, and
they're getting ready for ArtW Walk. But
any more information, check out their
websites. So, that's it.
>> Perfect. Thank you, Mr. Porter. You'd
like to add anything? Um we were
fortunate enough uh service safety
director Woody and I to attend um the
dedication for the new uh oak tree at
the fairgrounds for America 250. I just
encourage everybody if you have an
opportunity to head out there. Uh we had
the the color guard from the police
department there. It was a it was a nice
celebration. So but we look forward to
more for the anniversary.
>> Very nice. Miss Woody, anything?
Miss Hall?
Miss Nettles, I can't forget you. You're
good. All right, we'll move on to
announcement of scheduled meetings,
please.
>> I have um May 18th or I'm sorry, the
next regular sessions of council will be
May 18th, 2026 at 6:30 p.m. here in
council chambers and then again on June
8th, 2026 at 6:30 p.m. here in council
chambers.
Uh any regular schedule or I'm sorry,
let's move on. So so the special
scheduled meetings will include the code
enforcement one we talked about.
>> Yeah. Um that would be May 15th. Okay.
>> 7:30 and 1897 conference room.
>> Okay. And then regular scheduled
committee meetings, please. I have
service committee meeting May 14th, 2026
at 7:30 a.m. in 1897 conference room and
then administrative committee meeting
May 22nd, 2026 at 2 p.m. in the 1897
conference room. The code enforcement
was in my regular one, but that's okay.
>> Oh, I see it.
>> Sorry.
>> It's okay
>> if I skip if I skip I miss something and
it's
>> I will put it up over.
>> All right. Anyways, reading of bills. I
have one for publication for M MNCO for
publication of permanent ordinance 8-26
for $5125.
>> Mr. Bisjack.
>> Thank you, Mr. President. I move that we
pay the bills.
>> Second.
>> We have a motion and a second to pay the
bill. All in favor signify by saying I.
>> I.
>> Motion carries. We have no need for
executive session. I will entertain a
motion to adjurnn.
>> So move, Mr. President.
>> Mr. Rej
>> second.
>> We have a motion and a second to
adjurnn. All in favor?
>> I don't want to adjourn.
>> I'm going to say it here.
>> I
>> All right, we're ajourned, folks. Have a
nice evening.
The Frankie Smith Funeral Home and
Crematory in Lancaster and the Johnson
Smith Funeral Home in Baltimore have a
long and wonderful history of serving
our community. Feel free to give us a
call at 74-653652.
Stop in and see us at either of our two
locations, 405 North Columbus Street in
Lancaster and 207 South Main Street in
Baltimore. Respect for tradition, regard
for change.
>> Life moves fast and Buckeye is here to
keep you moving. New dream job?
Celebrate with a ride that feels just as
exciting. Passing the keys to your new
teen driver. Treat yourself to an
upgrade you'll love. Family getting
bigger? Buckeye's got the perfect
spacious, safety packed vehicle for
every new arrival. Wherever life takes
you, Buckeye Nissan, Georgeesville
Nissan, Buckeye Honda, and Buckeye
Toyota are ready to drive you forward.
Your life, your car, your choice. Choose
Buckeye.